<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Deb's Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[A personal space on the internet to share learnings and works]]></description><link>https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 11:24:43 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[My Year of 2023 - 2 steps forward, one step back]]></title><description><![CDATA[Starting.. 2023 started off well for me. I forced myself to go to our office meetup (1st to 7th Jan 2023) in Bangalore (social anxiety , yay…]]></description><link>https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/2023-year-in-review/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/2023-year-in-review/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 19:40:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;h3&gt;Starting..&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2023 started off well for me. I forced myself to go to our office meetup (1st to 7th Jan 2023) in Bangalore (social anxiety , yay!)  and gave an internal talk on “Backend Development” to 30+ devs in my org division(My manager pushed me). I loved meeting my collegues. I also presented  and talked about the projects I worked on in the last 2 years at the company. It was a big deal for me, because I have intense stage fright and anxiety about speaking in front of people and I avoid it if I can. I realized that, to get over it, I just need to do it more of it. Simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led a project end to end for the first time with a team of 4 devs. I led the backend and other than creating the technical architecture and high-level/low-level backend designs, was also responsible for managing the project (roadmap, timelines, sprints, ownership of deadlines, quality of builds, deliverables, improvements to the product etc). Made many many mistakes, specially when it came to communication across cross-functional teams (Data Science and Data Engineering) and learnt from them. Learnt to get over my intense dislike of following up on people or asking for status updates or pushing people to deliver things. Or even taking the lead or being more assertive. It was extremely exhausting and I hated it most of the time, I wanted to go back into my shell and hide in the safety of invisibility, but looking back I realize how important it was for me, and I should do it more.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have also been working on two more projects in the last few months ( For a major Beverages Company and a well known Management Consulting Company(ongoing)) and did a little bit of Product along with my technical responsibilities, I was more client facing, creating BRDs (Business Requirement Document) and doing client calls, doing product research etc. I got a lot of critical feedback from my manager on this, sort of failed spectacularly at time management and communication and got burned out in the end. My manager wanted to groom me from an SDE3 to a Technical Product Manager role, which I am very new to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Attended PyCon on behalf of my company and it inspired me to want to improve my speaking skills, have formed a small group of folks and we are going to work on our speaking skills together  this year and help each other improve by  providing feedback, critical analysis and sharing resources among ourselves that could help us. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Other than the projects I was leading, I have also participated in the interview process at my company for the first time in my career this year, I have taken 5 Design and Architecture interviews and 3 Coding round interviews till now, for TL (Team Lead) and EM(Engineering Manager) roles. Also onboarded one Team Lead ( who I helped hire) for one of my projects recently. I was scared to take the first interview, but after that I have been thoroughly enjoying learning about what the candidates had worked on in their companies, their stories, understanding and evaluating their thought process and how they solve problems. It’s fascinating and insightful and extremely fun. Having been an interviewer now I  no longer see interviews as scary but a fun process of learning things I didn’t know before. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have also participated in freshers training at my company for the first time, reviewing and rating their work, mentoring and helping create roadmaps for upskilling engineers on backend technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have mentored five women engineers as part of an internal Women in Tech initiative started at the company this year. Helped them with career doubts, done check-in calls and had some discussions regarding challenges faced by my mentees and how to navigate them based on my own experiences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Side projects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I worked on a small todo app at the start of the year - &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/debamitra/todo-app/tree/brainydo-dev&quot;&gt;https://github.com/debamitra/todo-app/tree/brainydo-dev&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I started working on a platform for  helping folks learn AI. Didn’t continue after a few weeks. Hope to pick it back up sometime in future. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/debamitra/ailearninglinks&quot;&gt;https://github.com/debamitra/ailearninglinks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Started an AI Study group with a few folks with similar goals. We met up online for a few weeks and made some progress with learning math (Linear algebra basics).  Didn’t progress  beyond that as we got busy with other things but would love to get back to studying AI fundamentals again sometime, I specially wanted to work through this course by David Malan on AI - &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs50.harvard.edu/ai/2024/&quot;&gt;https://cs50.harvard.edu/ai/2024/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Worked on the codebase for three months from August to October on a project called &lt;strong&gt;Plexbox&lt;/strong&gt; ( &lt;a href=&quot;https://plexbox.app/&quot;&gt;https://plexbox.app/&lt;/a&gt;) with a small team of devs. This project is the brainchild of and led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://duttakapil.com/&quot;&gt;Kapil Dutta&lt;/a&gt;. Plexbox currently allows a user to build web pages quickly and easily using a simple click action and a dropdown to create in-position html components like headers, images, buttons etc. This was my first experience with a proper collaborative side-project that had long term clarity and vision and was super exciting  to work on, from scratch. Had various kinds of learnings from it. Really struggled with mental models related to web development specially UI, programming in general and identified a lot of areas I would do well to focus on to improve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2024&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I generally do not retrospect on the past and have this idea that I am still stuck(in a rut), but I realized, I may be slow but I am moving. Every action I take, adds to my experience of life and every action I run away from, subtracts from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, I will objectively evaluate every opportunity for growth and change that presents itself to me and execute it  to the best of my ability regardless of how scared I am or how much I may fail at it or how tedious it feels. I want to be a better speaker and better leader at work. Personally, I want to improve my tech skills and share my learnings in a simple way in the form of blog posts(with cute like doodles sprinkled around because I like to draw) etc to create value for others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, here are some specific things I started in December and are ongoing -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to do the TeachYourselfCS (&lt;a href=&quot;https://teachyourselfcs.com/&quot;&gt;https://teachyourselfcs.com/&lt;/a&gt;)  course ever since I came to know about it. I never studied properly in college and what I knew, I have forgotten since it was more than 15 years ago. I want to use the current tools available like GPT and all the online resources to learn and work on things in a way that wasn’t possible before. So that I can do deep dives in things and understand how they work or don’t work at the lowest levels. Build better mental models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Operating Systems and the NAND to Tetris course/ Computer System Architecture -&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going through my old college textbook on OS - Operating System Concepts, by Abraham Silberschatz &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Going through Ben Eaters 8-bit computer series - &lt;a href=&quot;https://eater.net/8bit/&quot;&gt;https://eater.net/8bit/&lt;/a&gt;. I wish I could build it as well, but the kit is very costly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading about microprocessors, instruction sets etc from my college textbook - Morris Mano’s Computer System Architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Went through this resource to learn about the python interpreter and few YouTube tutorials on python internals  - &lt;a href=&quot;https://aosabook.org/en/500L/a-python-interpreter-written-in-python.html&quot;&gt;https://aosabook.org/en/500L/a-python-interpreter-written-in-python.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I started the adventofcode but didn’t do more than 3-4 problems sadly. I would like to finish it. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/debamitra/adventofcode&quot;&gt;https://github.com/debamitra/adventofcode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Ramana for his encouragement and his blog post on the same topic which pushed me into writing and posting this. Here is his year in review post:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.vramana.com/posts/2023_retrospective/&quot;&gt;https://blog.vramana.com/posts/2023_retrospective/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some more year in reviews you may like to read :&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://duttakapil.com/posts/year-in-review-2023&quot;&gt;https://duttakapil.com/posts/year-in-review-2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ksridhar.dev/my-2023-a-year-of-challenges-and-triumphs&quot;&gt;https://ksridhar.dev/my-2023-a-year-of-challenges-and-triumphs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://una.im/2023-in-review/&quot;&gt;https://una.im/2023-in-review/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://addyo.substack.com/p/23-lessons-in-2023&quot;&gt;https://addyo.substack.com/p/23-lessons-in-2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.cassidoo.co/post/bye-bye-2023/&quot;&gt;https://blog.cassidoo.co/post/bye-bye-2023/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can be reached at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:debamitra.mukherjee@gmail.com&quot;&gt;debamitra.mukherjee@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; , or connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/debamitra_&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/debamitramukherjee/&quot;&gt;linkedin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Story of a Rejected Promise (As a Javascript Programmer)]]></title><description><![CDATA[Stop waiting, start doing! -Unknown Javascript is inherently synchronous, i.e. it runs only one line of code at a time and in a sequential…]]></description><link>https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/async-javascript/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/async-javascript/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 May 2021 19:40:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop waiting, start doing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Unknown&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Javascript is inherently synchronous, i.e. it runs only one line of code at a time and in a sequential manner. This means if a task has a long wait-time, e.g making a network call and then waiting for the call to return a response, it can block the whole program for a while. Also while waiting, no other task can run, which is very inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asynchronicity is when multiple tasks can be dome simulteneously, for instance, while the the program waits for the response of a network call, it can do some other task like display some graphics or compute some numbers or something else. This is made possible through &lt;strong&gt;asynchronous programming&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the ways to achieve this is via &lt;strong&gt;Callbacks&lt;/strong&gt;. A function with a slow task, is passed an extra argument, a callback function. Once this slow function is called it starts its task and when it finishes, the callback function is called inside it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Callbacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 590px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/5afe2/callback1.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 79.72972972972973%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAQABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAAAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEDAgX/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHtvKLEA//EABoQAQACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECEQAQEiH/2gAIAQEAAQUCZYOonjdR6D//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAXEAEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAICEx/9oACAEBAAY/AoYp/8QAHBAAAgICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAIRBBMVGB/9oACAEBAAE/IUcQhOAotalgeFEISu3P/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABDDz//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQMBAT8QP//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABD/2gAIAQIBAT8QP//EABwQAAICAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAERACEQMUFRcf/aAAgBAQABPxBzQjucaXmGsiAwoLgtgAI2JywQUqzn/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Callback&quot;
        title=&quot;Callback&quot;
        src=&quot;/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/1c72d/callback1.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/a80bd/callback1.jpg 148w,
/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/1c91a/callback1.jpg 295w,
/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/1c72d/callback1.jpg 590w,
/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/a8a14/callback1.jpg 885w,
/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/fbd2c/callback1.jpg 1180w,
/debs-blog/static/254d01ddffe14a50b1591b1d5cb1081c/5afe2/callback1.jpg 1730w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;deckgo-highlight-code language=&quot;javascript&quot;  terminal=&quot;carbon&quot; theme=&quot;blackboard&quot; &gt;
          &lt;code slot=&quot;code&quot;&gt;function doHomework( questions, chocolate, eatChocolate ) {
 //do homework stuff
 .
 .
 eatChocolate(chocolate); 
}
doHomework(questions, chocolate, eatChocolate);&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/deckgo-highlight-code&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Problem with Callbacks? - Callback Hell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 590px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/44fe8/callback2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 68.24324324324324%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAOABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECBf/EABQBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAD/2gAMAwEAAhADEAAAAdmmygD/xAAYEAEBAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABECEP/aAAgBAQABBQLVtwhnkfP/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAWEAADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAICH/2gAIAQEABj8CKv8A/8QAGxAAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEBIRAxQXH/2gAIAQEAAT8h2FTN7yRZwiBA+Y//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAELDP/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPxA//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPxA//8QAGhABAQADAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAITFRcf/aAAgBAQABPxBHK2BPBm8NoAUFerzFFifcG6JfcZRtU3xwITP/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Too many nested Callbacks&quot;
        title=&quot;Too many nested Callbacks&quot;
        src=&quot;/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/1c72d/callback2.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/a80bd/callback2.jpg 148w,
/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/1c91a/callback2.jpg 295w,
/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/1c72d/callback2.jpg 590w,
/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/a8a14/callback2.jpg 885w,
/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/fbd2c/callback2.jpg 1180w,
/debs-blog/static/3220cd90c5f9a497f3b46c5d3947924e/44fe8/callback2.jpg 2145w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;deckgo-highlight-code language=&quot;javascript&quot;  terminal=&quot;carbon&quot; theme=&quot;blackboard&quot; &gt;
          &lt;code slot=&quot;code&quot;&gt;doHomework(questions, function(){
	eatChocolate(chocolate, function(){
		washHands(soap, function(){
			play();
		});
	});
});&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;/deckgo-highlight-code&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above example has only three nested functions but the indented nesting can go on and on resulting in difficult to read code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To resolve this problem we have &lt;strong&gt;Promises&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Promise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A promise is a simple javascript object with mutable state i.e the value it holds changes. When a promise is first created, its state is &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;pending&lt;/code&gt; and the value it holds is &lt;em&gt;undefined&lt;/em&gt; . Later when the promise resolves to a value or gets rejected and returns, the handler passed to &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;.then()&lt;/code&gt; gets executed with this resolved value or rejected error as the case may be.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 590px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/debs-blog/static/a8a34f1dd613fa7496f427ec2a402d7b/054c0/promise2.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 142.56756756756758%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAdABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAGAABAQADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAgABAwX/xAAUAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHtnYRRiOYUY//EABsQAAMAAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABESFBEBIx/9oACAEBAAEFAt2l5gy4Xm1k6o//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEDAQE/AR//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAECAQE/AR//xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAw/9oACAEBAAY/Ak//xAAbEAADAQADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREhMUFRcf/aAAgBAQABPyF3NFS3CRxO9kbbPs5ejZcoN2dHb0StH5H/2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAEIDIDP/EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQMBAT8QH//EABQRAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAACD/2gAIAQIBAT8QH//EAB0QAQACAgMBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAEAESExQVFxYfH/2gAIAQEAAT8Qzgwq8Gpe2YCcL3iDnMSGuwXdRHOLx8lz9R4F9tahwMunUMGV3NAi1mA9d8wro+k//9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Promises, promises&quot;
        title=&quot;Promises, promises&quot;
        src=&quot;/debs-blog/static/a8a34f1dd613fa7496f427ec2a402d7b/1c72d/promise2.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/debs-blog/static/a8a34f1dd613fa7496f427ec2a402d7b/a80bd/promise2.jpg 148w,
/debs-blog/static/a8a34f1dd613fa7496f427ec2a402d7b/1c91a/promise2.jpg 295w,
/debs-blog/static/a8a34f1dd613fa7496f427ec2a402d7b/1c72d/promise2.jpg 590w,
/debs-blog/static/a8a34f1dd613fa7496f427ec2a402d7b/054c0/promise2.jpg 633w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On executing above program, when the interpreter reaches this line &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;checkForExtraPen().then&lt;/code&gt; it executes the following steps - &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it puts the  HANDLER we passed into .then() , in the MICROTASK QUEUE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it executes the EXECUTOR FUNCTION [that we passed to new Promise()].&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;executor function then calls reject() and populates promise object with information passed to the reject call ie. “Oops Sorry!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;interpreter goes to next line and prints “..other work”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it then takes out the HANDLER from microtask queue and executes it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;value&lt;/code&gt; passed to the handler is information returned from resolve(). In our case it is &lt;em&gt;undefined&lt;/em&gt;. We get &lt;code class=&quot;language-text&quot;&gt;error&lt;/code&gt; because our promise was rejected, which is printed out “Oops Sorry!”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this concludes our Promise story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently looking for work in the Javascript domain, if you know of any remote openings in an innovative company with a healthy employee culture , please do share, I can be reached at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:debamitra.mukherjee@gmail.com&quot;&gt;debamitra.mukherjee@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; , or connect with me on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/debamitra_&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/debamitramukherjee/&quot;&gt;linkedin&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading, hope you enjoyed it. &lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[A project-based learning attempt at Go, Part-1]]></title><description><![CDATA[Go is an open-source general-purpose programming language created by some Google folks sometime in the late 2000s. Okay, I think this…]]></description><link>https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/go-journey-part1/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/go-journey-part1/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 18 Aug 2020 22:40:32 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Go is an open-source general-purpose programming language created by some Google folks sometime in the late 2000s. Okay, I think this introduction is vague enough to be sightly annoying and yet, good enough by my standards, now onwards with the planning of the itinerary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A person on discord says to me, “Tour of Go” is the first step to enlightenment, so of course I went and completed that one first. It was tedious in parts, adapting and learning new syntax but I finally hopped, skipped and jumped my way through it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://tour.golang.org/welcome/1&quot;&gt;Tour of Go&lt;/a&gt; -
Gained very basic familiarity with the syntax of Go, played around with Go code examples. Learnt basic concepts and implementations like maps and slices , pointers and interfaces,functions,closures and structs, goroutines and channels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Concurrency (Go) - Went through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gA4YXUJX7t8&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; video to learn about concurrency concepts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Developer Envionment Setup - Downloaded and installed go from their &lt;a href=&quot;https://golang.org/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;. Set up the IDE (I am using &lt;a href=&quot;https://vscode.rocks/&quot;&gt;VS Code&lt;/a&gt; ). Then installed Go extension for VS Code etc etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Qtk9FFOoT5M&quot;&gt;Structuring Go apps&lt;/a&gt; - This very useful talk covered the following principles and guidelines for structuring a Go app, generally speaking.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A flat structure is what you can kind of default to in the beginning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next we can try to break it up into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.callicoder.com/golang-packages/#:~:text=Go%20Package,following%20syntax%20%2D%20package&quot;&gt;packages&lt;/a&gt;  this is called a layered architecture -&gt; UI, Business logic, dependencies. But this has some problems.How do we share data between packages? Naming is difficult again. Circular dependencies happen, difficult to track.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lets try breaking up into modules &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lets try grouping  by context (Domain driven Design) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hexagonal Architecture - Enables you to change a part of the application without changing everything else&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ends with proposing that trying to design the project structure using either Domain-Driven-Design or Hexagonal architechture might be a good way to go. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the &lt;strong&gt;Go&lt;/strong&gt; people on Twitter.(Important step)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quii.gitbook.io/learn-go-with-tests/&quot;&gt;Learn Go with Tests&lt;/a&gt; - Learning through Test Driven development(TDD) is a great way to incorporate good coding practices early on. This is a terrific hands-on resource that I am currently going through. TDD is a good process for writing bug-free,high quality, maintainable, readable, and easy to refactor code in the long run.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My next step is to build my first small project which is basically going to be a clone of &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com&quot;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, here’s a quote to make this post look prettier than it actually is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Because it’s not perfect, let’s not bother.”
That’s crazy! Even if we take three steps forward and two and a half back it’s still going
half a foot forward.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why learn Go? (As a Java Backend Developer)]]></title><description><![CDATA[The question isnt why?
But why not..  Java is still the  go-to language for large-scale enterprise software development due to its mature…]]></description><link>https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/java-to-golang/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://debamitra.github.io/debs-blog/java-to-golang/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Aug 2020 22:12:03 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question isnt why?
But why not..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; max-width: 590px; &quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/debs-blog/static/1cae082a3fbfe3933c9322a60ad8adb0/d4b53/java-go.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 49.32432432432432%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAKABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwAAAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECBf/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEA/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHdGygsT//EABgQAQADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIAECEy/9oACAEBAAEFAlFyNN//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAWEAEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAISD/2gAIAQEABj8CRcf/xAAZEAEAAwEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABABExECH/2gAIAQEAAT8hVHkSN1USDqIOnf/aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQPN//xAAWEQEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABACH/2gAIAQMBAT8QTIwv/8QAFhEBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARAh/9oACAECAQE/EB2f/8QAGxAAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREAIRAxQXH/2gAIAQEAAT8QKCzJ5Nexgrm+g+KGAg+iaCFY/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Java To Golang&quot;
        title=&quot;Java To Golang&quot;
        src=&quot;/debs-blog/static/1cae082a3fbfe3933c9322a60ad8adb0/1c72d/java-go.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/debs-blog/static/1cae082a3fbfe3933c9322a60ad8adb0/a80bd/java-go.jpg 148w,
/debs-blog/static/1cae082a3fbfe3933c9322a60ad8adb0/1c91a/java-go.jpg 295w,
/debs-blog/static/1cae082a3fbfe3933c9322a60ad8adb0/1c72d/java-go.jpg 590w,
/debs-blog/static/1cae082a3fbfe3933c9322a60ad8adb0/d4b53/java-go.jpg 853w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java is still the  go-to language for large-scale enterprise software development due to its mature ecosystem of libraries and frameworks targetted to the enterprise,strong developer community, durability from having been tried and tested in production environments for over two decades, scalability and ease of integration, its ability to evolve over time and keep adapting to modern best practices and many more reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But considering the fast changing landscape of software development, it is necessary for any software engineer to keep adding new tools to their developer toolbox, and learning a new language can sometimes broaden one’s perspective and also improve their abilities when working with Java as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Go or Golang is a language that can be quite fun and useful to learn in this case. Go was designed originally as more of a systems-level programming language with features of C/C++ but without their problems. It takes the best from them and Java to give you a better language to work with. Go is simple to learn, fast, is slightly more opinionated about best practices for writing clean and efficient code, handles concurrency really really well and Go code is quite easy to reason about unlike Java.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;to be continued…&lt;/h2&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>